<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>project | Ashleigh Filtness</title><link>/category/project/</link><atom:link href="/category/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>project</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:28 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu4f8ab371607c3a79349700d7bceeea31_25302_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>project</title><link>/category/project/</link></image><item><title>ICAROS</title><link>/project/icaros/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/icaros/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://icaros.lboro.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ICAROS (International Research Centre to Investigate the Effects of Vehicle Automation on Vulnerable Road Users)&lt;/a> – part-funded by Research England – brings together researchers from Loughborough’s University’s Transport Safety Research Center(TSRC), Queensland University of Technology and Tongji University. The International research centre – led by TSRC– investigates the safety of vulnerable road users (VRU) as driverless cars – or connected and autonomous vehicles (CAVs) – become more prevalent. ICAROS is nominated for a Loughborough University CALIBRE award &lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/research/calibre-awards/nominees/icaros/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/research/calibre-awards/nominees/icaros/&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/departments/design-school/whats-happening/news/2019/i3.html">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/departments/design-school/whats-happening/news/2019/i3.html&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>iDreams</title><link>/project/idreams/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/idreams/</guid><description>&lt;p>iDreams is funded by the European Commission under Horizon 2020 to develop, test and validate a motoring platform which considers the driver state, the vehicle, and the driving context. The monitoring system is grounded in a defined ‘Safety Tolerance Zone’ which dictates boundaries of safe/unsafe operation. Both real time and post trip interventions are employed to mitigate driving risks across 4 user groups (cars, trucks, rail and coaches).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/">https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/may/new-eu-project-improve-road-safety/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/may/new-eu-project-improve-road-safety/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bus Driver Fatigue</title><link>/project/busdrivers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/busdrivers/</guid><description>&lt;p>This mixed methods research programme used focus groups, interviews, survey and on-road investigation to understand sleepiness and fatigue in London city bus drivers, and suggest potential solutions to mitigate the impact on safety. The project was commissioned by Transport for London and conducted in collaboration with Dr Anna Anund and colleagues from the Swedish National Road and Transport Research Institute (VTI).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/august/bus-driver-fatigue-research/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/august/bus-driver-fatigue-research/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://content.tfl.gov.uk/bus-driver-fatigue-report.pdf">http://content.tfl.gov.uk/bus-driver-fatigue-report.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SafetyCube</title><link>/project/safetycube/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 15:48:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/safetycube/</guid><description>&lt;p>SafetyCube (Safety CaUsation, Benefits and Efficiency) was a research project funded by the European Commission under Horizon 2020, the objective of SafetyCube was to develop an
&lt;a href="https://www.safetycube-project.eu/safetycube-decision-support-system-may-2015/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">innovative road safety Decision Support System (DSS)&lt;/a> that enables policy-makers and stakeholders to select and implement the most appropriate strategies, measures and cost-effective approaches to reduce casualties of all road user types. The significance of this work was recognised by a
&lt;a href="https://www.roadsafetyawards.com/safetycube" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Prince Michael International Road Safety Award in 2019&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/december/road-safety-award-prince-michael-of-kent/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/december/road-safety-award-prince-michael-of-kent/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OSA &amp; Driving</title><link>/project/osadriving/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 16:08:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/osadriving/</guid><description>&lt;p>Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) and daytime driver sleepiness was the topic of my Ph.D (2011). In a series of driving simulator investigations this work demonstrated that OSA patients who have been using CPAP treatment for at least 1 year show no different in performance at driving in a simulator than healthy controls. However, OSA patients were more vulnerable to sleep loss, and without their CPAP treatment driving performance was significantly impaired compared to drivers of a similar age without OSA.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>