<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>project | Ashleigh Filtness</title><link>/category/project/</link><atom:link href="/category/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>project</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 23:48:34 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu4f8ab371607c3a79349700d7bceeea31_25302_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>project</title><link>/category/project/</link></image><item><title>Reducing the risk of sleep‐related crashes in young drivers</title><link>/project/sleepyoung/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 23:48:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/sleepyoung/</guid><description>&lt;p>This research aims to make the first steps towards developing an intervention which will improve the sleep health of newly licenced novice drivers and consequently reduce sleepiness-related road crashes. Young drivers are at a disproportionately greater risk of sleep-related crashes than older drivers. Traditionally, interventions to reduce driver sleepiness have been passive strategies targeted at the general population such as the introduction of &lt;em>“Tiredness kills take a break”&lt;/em> signs along motorways. This research addresses the gap by targeting those most at risk. A range of techniques (survey, focus group, expert panel interviews) will be used to understand situational factors which exacerbate young drivers risk and select intervention features with greatest potential to be effective. Ultimately, considerations and practical guidelines will be developed to support intervention development for enabling young drivers to reduce their own risk of sleep-related crashes. The project is funded by UK Department for Transport.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ICAROS</title><link>/project/icaros/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/icaros/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://icaros.lboro.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ICAROS (International Research Centre to Investigate the Effects of Vehicle Automation on Vulnerable Road Users)&lt;/a> – part-funded by Research England – brings together researchers from Loughborough’s University’s Transport Safety Research Center(TSRC), Queensland University of Technology and Tongji University. The International research centre – led by TSRC– investigates the safety of vulnerable road users (VRU) as driverless cars – or connected and autonomous vehicles (CAVs) – become more prevalent. ICAROS is nominated for a Loughborough University CALIBRE award - &lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/research/calibre-awards/nominees/icaros/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/research/calibre-awards/nominees/icaros/&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/departments/design-school/whats-happening/news/2019/i3.html">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/departments/design-school/whats-happening/news/2019/i3.html&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://icaros.lboro.ac.uk/">https://icaros.lboro.ac.uk/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>iDreams</title><link>/project/idreams/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/idreams/</guid><description>&lt;p>iDreams is funded by the European Commission under Horizon 2020 to develop, test and validate a motoring platform which considers the driver state, the vehicle, and the driving context. The monitoring system is grounded in a defined ‘Safety Tolerance Zone’ which dictates boundaries of safe/unsafe operation. Both real time and post trip interventions are employed to mitigate driving risks across 4 user groups (cars, trucks, rail and coaches)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/">https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/may/new-eu-project-improve-road-safety/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/may/new-eu-project-improve-road-safety/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/iDreams-uHasselt-%E2%80%93-by-Zologie.com-3.mp4">https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/iDreams-uHasselt-%E2%80%93-by-Zologie.com-3.mp4&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-idreams-kick-off-meeting-2019">
&lt;a data-fancybox="" href="/project/idreams/iDreams_hu575d92207305949a038e99d8ad10dcbb_2218790_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" data-caption="iDreams Kick Off meeting 2019">
&lt;img data-src="/project/idreams/iDreams_hu575d92207305949a038e99d8ad10dcbb_2218790_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" class="lazyload" alt="" width="4096" height="2730">
&lt;/a>
&lt;figcaption>
iDreams Kick Off meeting 2019
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>Caffeine and truck drivers</title><link>/project/caffeine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/caffeine/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most effective ways to counteract sleepiness when driving is to have a caffeinated drink and a nap. It is common advice given to truck drivers if they feel sleepy to have a caffeinated drink. However, caffeine is addictive. When this advice is repeatedly given it is possible some drivers may become regular consumers of high amounts of caffeine. This project set out to compare truck drivers who report drinking 5 or more caffeinated drinks every day with truck drivers that drink 1 caffeinated drink per day. High caffeine drinkers felt sleepier, got less sleep and had poorer diets, drank more alcohol and were more likely to smoke. Importantly the high caffeine use did not reduce the number of crashes drivers had, so it appears that caffeine is not beneficial in high amounts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project was complete while on a research visit to the Virginia Tech Transport Institute (VTTI)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fatigue and Sleepiness in Tunnelling Operations</title><link>/project/tideway/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/tideway/</guid><description>&lt;p>Workers in the tunnelling sector are exposed to a wide range of workplace factors that can increase their vulnerability to fatigue, including the physical environment, variable shift patterns, manual and physical work, and repetitive and monotonous tasks. This study investigated how fatigue/sleepiness is experienced and handled within the industry using the Tideway project as a case study. The project was funded by Tideway. Using qualitative research techniques we spoke to frontline workers, supervisors/managers, middle managers and those involved in shift scheduling. All groups recognised that tunnelling workers experience fatigue/sleepiness, the frontline workers were less likely to see this as impacting safety than the other groups. There are opportunities for the industry to improve fatigue/sleepiness management but this will require a shift of workplace culture.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bus Driver Fatigue</title><link>/project/busdrivers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/busdrivers/</guid><description>&lt;p>This mixed methods research programme used focus groups, interviews, survey and on-road investigation to understand sleepiness and fatigue in London city bus drivers, and suggest potential solutions to mitigate the impact on safety. The project was commissioned by Transport for London and conducted in collaboration with Dr Anna Anund and colleagues from the Swedish National Road and Transport Research Institute (VTI).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/august/bus-driver-fatigue-research/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/august/bus-driver-fatigue-research/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://content.tfl.gov.uk/bus-driver-fatigue-report.pdf">http://content.tfl.gov.uk/bus-driver-fatigue-report.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SafetyCube</title><link>/project/safetycube/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 15:48:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/safetycube/</guid><description>&lt;p>SafetyCube (Safety CaUsation, Benefits and Efficiency) was a research project funded by the European Commission under Horizon 2020, the objective of SafetyCube was to develop an
&lt;a href="https://www.safetycube-project.eu/safetycube-decision-support-system-may-2015/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">innovative road safety Decision Support System (DSS)&lt;/a> that enables policy-makers and stakeholders to select and implement the most appropriate strategies, measures and cost-effective approaches to reduce casualties of all road user types. The significance of this work was recognised by a
&lt;a href="https://www.roadsafetyawards.com/safetycube" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Prince Michael International Road Safety Award in 2019&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y-mVUde3knU">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y-mVUde3knU&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/december/road-safety-award-prince-michael-of-kent/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/december/road-safety-award-prince-michael-of-kent/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;figure id="figure-receiving-the-prince-michael-international-road-safety-awards-2019">
&lt;a data-fancybox="" href="/project/safetycube/SafetyCube_hu57b7d43b78d15d41e692bf22a49b3cc6_2352218_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" data-caption="Receiving the Prince Michael International Road Safety Awards 2019">
&lt;img data-src="/project/safetycube/SafetyCube_hu57b7d43b78d15d41e692bf22a49b3cc6_2352218_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" class="lazyload" alt="" width="4032" height="3024">
&lt;/a>
&lt;figcaption>
Receiving the Prince Michael International Road Safety Awards 2019
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure id="figure-safetycube-conference-2018">
&lt;a data-fancybox="" href="/project/safetycube/SafetyCubeb_hu974464f88636cf25fe22deb0a9ba30cf_1335154_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" data-caption="SafetyCube Conference 2018">
&lt;img data-src="/project/safetycube/SafetyCubeb_hu974464f88636cf25fe22deb0a9ba30cf_1335154_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg" class="lazyload" alt="" width="3872" height="2592">
&lt;/a>
&lt;figcaption>
SafetyCube Conference 2018
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>Sleep-related crashes</title><link>/project/crashes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 22:56:57 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/crashes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Over a series of investigations I have worked with police recorded crash data, and self-report experience of those who have had a sleep-related crash to identify common characteristics of sleep crashes. Our findings have show that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Sleep crashes are more common on high speed than low speed roads.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When sleep crashes do happen on low speed roads they have more severe outcomes than not sleep related crashes on the same roads.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sleep related crashes on low and high speed roads have similar characteristics: younger drivers (16-24y) are over represented, males are over represented, more likely to hit a stationary object, greater likelihood of severe outcome.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sleep related crashes are under reported, many people who have had a sleep related crash report that the police were not informed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some jurisdictions who recognise the under reporting of sleep related crashes apply a proxy definition making an assumption that all crashes that fit set criteria are treated as sleep related.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Applying a proxy definition can influence the overall observed characteristics of sleep crashes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Sleep loss and visual attention</title><link>/project/attention/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/attention/</guid><description>&lt;p>Over a series of studies this project assessed factors that affect drivers’ ability to detect changes in visual information; exploring whether sleepiness impairs change detection. The work was funded by the NRMA-ACT Road Safety Trust.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, the research found that drivers are best at detecting changes that involve other road users and targets with high safety relevance. The impact of safety relevance is greatest in demanding situations, e.g. when the visual environment is cluttered or at high travel speeds. Accuracy for change detection was maintained after sleep loss. There is limited evidence that sleep loss impairs efficiency of change detection in visually cluttered urban scenes, but not in rural scenes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Train driver fatigue and sleepiness</title><link>/project/traindriver/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2017 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/traindriver/</guid><description>&lt;p>A signal passed at danger (SPAD) is considered one of the biggest safety breaches in rail. A series of focus groups with train drivers were conducted to discuss factors which can contribute to SPADS. This project used the existing focus groups to complete a targeted analysis of all mentions of fatigue or sleepiness. Drivers at all focus groups experienced fatigue/sleepiness despite each organisation having countermeasures in place aiming to reduce fatigue/sleepiness. Organisational culture was a barrier to effective fatigue/sleepiness management.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Level crossing safety</title><link>/project/rlx/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/rlx/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have been involved in two different projects investigating road safety at level crossings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Passive rail crossings have no active warning systems to assist drivers. They are reliant on their own perception to make the decision whether it is safe to cross or not. To investigate human capabilities to do this, we asked participants to observe approaching trains. Drivers can accurately detect that a train is moving when the train gets within 1.6km of them. Most people underestimate how quickly the train is travelling, (despite being confident in their speed estimate) and report that it would be safe to cross under situations where lights would have been activated at an active level crossing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a separate on-road investigation of driver behaviour at passive stop sign level crossings, we observed that 40% of drivers did not completely stop. Those drivers who did not stop spent less time visually checking for trains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although, most drivers try to be safe at level crossings, the design of passive crossings can make it difficult for them to do so.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sleepy eyes</title><link>/project/eyes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 22:56:57 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/eyes/</guid><description>&lt;p>OMost people have some awareness of how sleepy they are. If someone falls asleep when they are driving it is rare that they will not have tried to do something to prevent sleepiness beforehand e.g. opening a window, talking to a passenger. Taking an action to try and counteract their sleepiness demonstrates that they are aware of their tiredness. However, some people report that they are not able to tell when they are sleepy. This project investigated how subjective feelings about the eyes relate to objective observation of driving performance. 10 different eye symptoms were trialled with sleepy participants driving a simulator and on a real road. The two symptoms with strongest links to sleepiness were having ‘heavy eyelids’ and ‘difficulty keeping eyes open’, after this ‘eye strain’ and ‘difficulty focusing’ were next most associated with sleepiness. Results suggest that drivers who are struggling to identify sleepiness could be helped with the advice ‘stop driving if you feel sleepy and/or have heavy eyelids or difficulty keeping your eyes open’.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project was completed while on a research visit to the Swedish National Road and Transport Research Institute (VTI)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sleep and daytime sleepiness in new mothers</title><link>/project/mums/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/mums/</guid><description>&lt;p>It is well known that lack of sleep increases sleepiness during the daytime. New mothers are highly likely to experience daytime sleepiness because of disruption to night time sleep. This study followed new mothers for 18 weeks after their baby was born. On weeks 6, 12 and 18 after giving birth mothers were asked to record their sleep and rate how sleepy they felt. The amount of night time sleep remained the same at each time point, as did the number of times the mothers were woken during the night, but the number of minutes they spent awake after each time of being woken reduced over time. Subjective sleepiness decreased at each time point. At week 18 half of the mothers were still experiencing excessive daytime sleepiness. Policy makers developing regulations for parental leave entitlements should be aware of this high prevalence of excessive daytime sleepiness and leave is long enough for daytime sleepiness to diminish to a manageable level prior to restarting work.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Young driver sleepiness</title><link>/project/oldyoung/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/oldyoung/</guid><description>&lt;p>This study aimed to investigate why younger men are overrepresented in sleep-related crashes compared to older men, is it because younger men are more vulnerable to the effects of sleep loss? Using the safe environment of a driving simulator driving performance of older (average age =67 years) men was compared to that of younger (average age =23 years) men, after their night time sleep had been restricted to 5 hours. After the sleep restriction the younger drivers had worse driving performance and more signs of sleepiness in EEG recordings than the older drivers. When both groups were fully rested driving performance did not differ between the two age groups. Results show that younger drivers are more vulnerable to the effects of sleep loss than older drivers.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>