<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Ashleigh Filtness</title><link>/project/</link><atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 15:00:10 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu4f8ab371607c3a79349700d7bceeea31_25302_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>/project/</link></image><item><title>Topmark Funding Article</title><link>/project/topmark/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 15:00:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/topmark/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Commercial Motor Article</title><link>/project/commercialmotor/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 15:00:23 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/commercialmotor/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Future Transport Event</title><link>/project/futuretransport/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 15:07:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/futuretransport/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Roadsafe article</title><link>/project/roadsafe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 14:51:42 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/roadsafe/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Active Training Team Podcast</title><link>/project/att/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 15:04:12 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/att/</guid><description/></item><item><title>ICAROS</title><link>/project/icaros/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/icaros/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://icaros.lboro.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ICAROS (International Research Centre to Investigate the Effects of Vehicle Automation on Vulnerable Road Users)&lt;/a> – part-funded by Research England – brings together researchers from Loughborough’s University’s Transport Safety Research Center(TSRC), Queensland University of Technology and Tongji University. The International research centre – led by TSRC– investigates the safety of vulnerable road users (VRU) as driverless cars – or connected and autonomous vehicles (CAVs) – become more prevalent. ICAROS is nominated for a Loughborough University CALIBRE award &lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/research/calibre-awards/nominees/icaros/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/research/calibre-awards/nominees/icaros/&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/departments/design-school/whats-happening/news/2019/i3.html">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/departments/design-school/whats-happening/news/2019/i3.html&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>iDreams</title><link>/project/idreams/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:49:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/idreams/</guid><description>&lt;p>iDreams is funded by the European Commission under Horizon 2020 to develop, test and validate a motoring platform which considers the driver state, the vehicle, and the driving context. The monitoring system is grounded in a defined ‘Safety Tolerance Zone’ which dictates boundaries of safe/unsafe operation. Both real time and post trip interventions are employed to mitigate driving risks across 4 user groups (cars, trucks, rail and coaches).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/">https://idreamsproject.eu/wp/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/may/new-eu-project-improve-road-safety/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/may/new-eu-project-improve-road-safety/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bus Driver Fatigue</title><link>/project/busdrivers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 15:57:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/busdrivers/</guid><description>&lt;p>This mixed methods research programme used focus groups, interviews, survey and on-road investigation to understand sleepiness and fatigue in London city bus drivers, and suggest potential solutions to mitigate the impact on safety. The project was commissioned by Transport for London and conducted in collaboration with Dr Anna Anund and colleagues from the Swedish National Road and Transport Research Institute (VTI).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/august/bus-driver-fatigue-research/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/august/bus-driver-fatigue-research/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://content.tfl.gov.uk/bus-driver-fatigue-report.pdf">http://content.tfl.gov.uk/bus-driver-fatigue-report.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Zeenews India Article</title><link>/project/zeenews/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 14:58:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/zeenews/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Chronicle Article</title><link>/project/thechronicle/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 14:58:38 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/thechronicle/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scimex Article</title><link>/project/scimex/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 14:44:32 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/scimex/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Medical Express Article</title><link>/project/medicalexpress/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 14:59:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/medicalexpress/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="do-you-know-the-signs-of-being-too-sleepy-to-drive">Do you know the signs of being too sleepy to drive?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>by Sandra Hutchinson, Queensland University of Technology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dr Ashleigh Filtness is looking for young drivers to take part in a new study to find out what factors lead people to get behind the wheel when they are tired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Drivers with tired eyes are three times more likely to cross the centre line, according to QUT research, which has pinpointed four eye symptoms to help drivers recognise the signs they are too sleepy to get behind the wheel.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dr Ashleigh Filtness, from QUT&amp;rsquo;s Centre for Accident Research &amp;amp; Road Safety - Queensland (CARRS-Q), said a study that tested 10 sleep-related eye symptoms found heavy eyelids, eye strain, difficulty focusing and difficulty keeping eyes open, were linked to sleepiness and impaired driving.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;This finding, published in the Journal of Sleep Research, offers a physical sign to help those behind the wheel identify when they are too sleepy to drive,&amp;rdquo; she said.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dr Filtness said the next step in her research was to investigate the on-road experiences of young drivers to find out what factors lead people to get behind the wheel when they are tired.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We are looking for young drivers who have experienced one or more of these sleep-related signs - heavy eyelids, eye strain, difficulty focusing and difficulty keeping eyes open - but have still driven, to take part in this new study,&amp;rdquo; she said.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Driver sleepiness or fatigue is one of the leading factors contributing to road crashes worldwide and in Australia it contributes to 20-30 per cent of all crashes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Current advice is &amp;lsquo;if you are sleepy, don&amp;rsquo;t drive&amp;rsquo; but the problem is some people struggle to comprehend the exact nature of their sleepiness and in particular pinpoint the signs of when to pull over.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dr Filtness said the research measured eye symptoms, subjective sleepiness and the driving performance of 16 people on real roads and in simulated driving conditions in Sweden, who completed 64 drives, averaging 150km each drive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>She said the number of line crossings per kilometre travelled by drivers was recorded to quantify impaired driving.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The results showed drivers who reported tired eyes on real roads crossed the centre line on average once every 14km, compared to those who reported not having tired eyes crossing once every 45km,&amp;rdquo; she said.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;In the simulator tests, drivers experiencing tired eyes crossed on average once every 9km, compared to those who did not have tired eyes crossing once every 111km.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We found drivers who experience one or more of the four eye symptoms linked to sleepiness are likely to report requiring greater effort to remain awake and be more likely to have unintentional line crossings - a sign of sleep-related driving impairment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Eye symptoms that are related to subjective sleepiness (heavy eyelids, eye strain, difficulty focusing and difficulty keeping eyes open) can be used to help drivers identify signs of sleepiness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To take part in the new online study, drivers must be aged 30 or younger, hold a provisional or open licence and drive at least three journeys per week.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SafetyCube</title><link>/project/safetycube/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 15:48:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/safetycube/</guid><description>&lt;p>SafetyCube (Safety CaUsation, Benefits and Efficiency) was a research project funded by the European Commission under Horizon 2020, the objective of SafetyCube was to develop an
&lt;a href="https://www.safetycube-project.eu/safetycube-decision-support-system-may-2015/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">innovative road safety Decision Support System (DSS)&lt;/a> that enables policy-makers and stakeholders to select and implement the most appropriate strategies, measures and cost-effective approaches to reduce casualties of all road user types. The significance of this work was recognised by a
&lt;a href="https://www.roadsafetyawards.com/safetycube" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Prince Michael International Road Safety Award in 2019&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/december/road-safety-award-prince-michael-of-kent/">https://www.lboro.ac.uk/media-centre/press-releases/2019/december/road-safety-award-prince-michael-of-kent/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Daily Mail Article</title><link>/project/dailymail/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 14:59:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/dailymail/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Telegraph Article</title><link>/project/telegraph/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 14:42:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/telegraph/</guid><description/></item><item><title>ABC Article</title><link>/project/abc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Feb 2012 14:48:43 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/abc/</guid><description/></item><item><title>OSA &amp; Driving</title><link>/project/osadriving/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 16:08:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>/project/osadriving/</guid><description>&lt;p>Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) and daytime driver sleepiness was the topic of my Ph.D (2011). In a series of driving simulator investigations this work demonstrated that OSA patients who have been using CPAP treatment for at least 1 year show no different in performance at driving in a simulator than healthy controls. However, OSA patients were more vulnerable to sleep loss, and without their CPAP treatment driving performance was significantly impaired compared to drivers of a similar age without OSA.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>